Virtual reality started for me in sort of an unusual place.
بدأت علاقتي بالواقع الإفتراضي بشكل غير متوقع.
It was the 1970s.
كان ذلك في السبعينيات
I got into the field very young: I was seven years old.
كنت صغراً عندما دخلت هذا المجال كنت في السابعة من عمري
And the tool that I used to access virtual reality
وكانت وسيلتي للدخول إلى الواقع الافتراضي
was the Evel Knievel stunt cycle.
لعبة (أيفل كنيفل) الدراجة الخارقة
This is a commercial for that particular item:
هذا الإعلان الترويجي لذلك المنتج
(Video) Voice-over: What a jump!
الفيديو - يا لها من قفزة!
Evel's riding the amazing stunt cycle.
(أيفل) يقود الدراجة المذهلة
That gyro-power sends him over 100 feet at top speed.
لقد رمت هذه القوة الخارقة به لأكثر من 100 قدم وبأقصى سرعة
Chris Milk: So this was my joy back then.
كريس ميلك: كانت هذه متعتي ذلك الوقت.
I rode this motorcycle everywhere.
لقد سرت بهذه الدراجة في كل مكان
And I was there with Evel Knievel; we jumped the Snake River Canyon together.
ورافقت (أيفل كنيفل)، قفزنا معًا فوق وادي (سنيك ريفر)
I wanted the rocket.
أردت الحصول على الصاروخ.
I never got the rocket, I only got the motorcycle.
لكنني لم أحصل عليه ابداً. فقط الدراجة.
I felt so connected to this world.
كنت مرتبطاً جداً بهذا العالم.
I didn't want to be a storyteller when I grew up, I wanted to be stuntman.
لم أرد أن أكون راوي قصص أبداً عندما أكبر، أردت أن تكون مهنتي رجل مخاطر
I was there. Evel Knievel was my friend.
لقد عشت هذا العالم كان (أيفل كنيفل) صديقي
I had so much empathy for him.
وتعاطفت معه كثيراً
But it didn't work out. (Laughter)
إلا أن ذلك لم يحصل. (ضحك)
I went to art school.
دخلت كلية الفنون
I started making music videos.
وبدأت بإخراج أفلام موسيقية
And this is one of the early music videos that I made:
وهذا واحد من أوائل الأفلام التي أخرجتها.
(Music: "Touch the Sky" by Kanye West)
(موسيقا: المس السماء لــ (كين ويست)
CM: You may notice some slight similarities here.
كريس ميلك: قد تلاحظون وجود بعض الشبه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I got that rocket.
وبأنني حصلت أخيراً على الصاروخ
So, now I'm a filmmaker, or, the beginning of a filmmaker,
وهكذا، أنا الآن صانع أفلام، أو مشروع صانع أفلام
and I started using the tools that are available to me as a filmmaker
وبدأت باستخدام الوسائل المتاحة لجعلي صانع أفلام
to try to tell the most compelling stories that I can to an audience.
يحاول رواية القصص الأكثر شعبية قدر المستطاع
And film is this incredible medium that allows us to feel empathy
والفيلم هو أكثر الوسائل روعة التي تجعلنا نتقمص شخصيات
for people that are very different than us
الناس المختلفين عنا بشكل كبير
and worlds completely foreign from our own.
ونعيش عوالمهم الغريبة عن عالمنا.
Unfortunately,
لسوء الحظ،
Evel Knievel did not feel the same empathy for us that we felt for him,
لم يبادلنا (أيفل كنيفل) نفس التعاطف الذي أبديناه له،
and he sued us for this video --
وتمت محاكمتنا على هذا الفيلم
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
shortly thereafter.
وبعد فترة قصيرة
On the upside, the man that I worshipped as a child,
ولسخرية الأقدار، الرجل الذي مجّدته في صغري
the man that I wanted to become as an adult,
والذي كان مثلي الأعلى وأردت أن أكون مثله عندما أكبر
I was finally able to get his autograph.
وأخيراً، حصلت على توقيعه
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Let's talk about film now.
لنتحدث عن الأفلام
Film, it's an incredible medium,
صناعة الأفلام، بيئة مذهلة
but essentially, it's the same now as it was then.
لم تتغير عبر الزمن
It's a group of rectangles that are played in a sequence.
هي كمجموعة مستطيلات صغيرة تشكل مربعاً
And we've done incredible things with those rectangles.
وقد قمنا بتكوينات مذهلة من هذه المستطيلات
But I started thinking about,
لكنني فكرت،
is there a way that I can use modern and developing technologies
هل من طريقة لاستغلال التقنيات الحديثة والمتطورة
to tell stories in different ways
واستخدامها لرواية القصص بشكل مختلف
and tell different kinds of stories
ولرواية أشكال مختلفة من القصص
that maybe I couldn't tell using the traditional tools of filmmaking
لن نستطيع روايتها بالشكل التقليدي لصناعة الأفلام
that we've been using for 100 years?
الذي نتبعه منذ 100 عام
So I started experimenting,
لذا بدأت بالتجربة،
and what I was trying to do was to build the ultimate empathy machine.
وكان الشيئ الذي حاولت بناءه بمثابة آلة تكسب تفاعلاً كبيراً
And here's one of the early experiments:
وهذه إحدى التجارب الأولية:
(Music)
(موسيقا)
So this is called "The Wilderness Downtown."
يدعى هذا بقلب المدينة البري
It was a collaboration with Arcade Fire.
بالتعاون مع فرقة (آركايد فاير)
It asked you to put in the address where you grew up at the beginning of it.
حيث يطلب منك كتابة عنوان نشأتك في البداية
It's a website.
إنه موقع الكتروني
And out of it starts growing these little boxes with different browser windows.
يخرج منه نوافذ صغيرة لمواقع أخرى
And you see this teenager running down a street,
ترى فيها ذلك المراهق يركض في الشارع
and then you see Google Street View and Google Maps imagery
ثم ترى الشارع بنمط محرك غوغل وخريطة غوغل المصورة
and you realize the street he's running down is yours.
وتلاحظ أن الشارع الذي يركض فيه الفتى هو شارعك.
And when he stops in front of a house, he stops in front of your house.
وعندما يقف أمام منزل، فإنه يقف أمام منزلك
And this was great, and I saw people having an even deeper emotional reaction
وكان ذلك عظيماً، وكان رد فعل الناس عاطفي بشكل عميق
to this than the things that I had made in rectangles.
أكثر مما فعلته في السابق، وموضوع المستطيلات.
And I'm essentially taking a piece of your history
لقد كنت فعلاً أقتطع جزءاً من تاريخك
and putting it inside the framing of the story.
وأضعه بداخل قصة.
But then I started thinking,
ثم فكرت،
okay, well that's a part of you,
حسناً، لقد كان هذا جزءاً منك
but how do I put all of you inside of the frame?
ولكن ماذا لو كنت أنت بكاملك داخل القصة؟
So to do that, I started making art installations.
وهكذا، بدات بإدخال أشكال فنية
And this is one called "The Treachery of Sanctuary."
يدعى هذا الفيلم " خيانة المقدسات".
It's a triptych. I'm going to show you the third panel.
وهو فيلم من ثلاث لوحات. ستشاهدون الآن اللوحة الثالثة.
(Music)
(موسيقا)
So now I've got you inside of the frame,
الآن أنت بداخل القصة
and I saw people having even more visceral emotional reactions
وكان رد فعل الناس تجاهها بقمة العمق
to this work than the previous one.
وأكبر بكثير من التجربة السابقة.
But then I started thinking about frames, and what do they represent?
ثم فكرت بالصورة السينيمائية بحد ذاتها، وماذا تمثل؟
And a frame is just a window.
فالصورة هي كنافذة
I mean, all the media that we watch -- television, cinema --
ما أعنيه هو، جميع ما نشاهده على شاشات التلفاز والسينما الخ...
they're these windows into these other worlds.
هي نوافذ على تلك العوالم الأخرى.
And I thought, well, great. I got you in a frame.
وفكرت، حسناً هذا عظيم. لقد استطعت وضعك في الصورة.
But I don't want you in the frame, I don't want you in the window,
لكنني لا أريدك في الصورة فقط، لا أريدك في النافذة
I want you through the window, I want you on the other side,
أريدك ان تعبر النافذة، إلى الجهة الأخرى
in the world, inhabiting the world.
إلى العالم الآخر، وتسكن هذا العالم.
So that leads me back to virtual reality.
وهذا ما أعادني بالتفكير إلى الواقع الافتراضي.
Let's talk about virtual reality.
لنتحدث عن الواقع الافتراضي.
Unfortunately,
لسوء الحظ،
talking about virtual reality is like dancing about architecture.
فإن الحديث عن الواقع الافتراضي كالرقص في فن العمارة!
And this is actually someone dancing about architecture in virtual reality.
وهذه حقيقة أحد ما يرقص في فن العمارة مستخدماً الواقع الافتراضي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, it's difficult to explain. Why is it difficult to explain?
أمر يصعب شرحه، لماذا يصعب شرحه؟
It's difficult because it's a very experiential medium.
امر صعب كوننا نتحدث عن بيئة تجريبية.
You feel your way inside of it.
يتم الإحساس بها عند الدخول إليها
It's a machine, but inside of it,
وكأنها آلة، لكنك ما إن تدخلها،
it feels like real life, it feels like truth.
حتى تشعر بانها حياة واقعية، بأنها الحقيقة.
And you feel present in the world that you're inside
وتشعر بوجودك في هذا العالم الذي دخلته
and you feel present with the people that you're inside of it with.
تشعر بتفاعلك مع الأشخاص الذين يشاركونك هذا الواقع
So, I'm going to show you a demo of a virtual reality film:
سأريكم عرضأ لفيلم واقع افتراضي:
a full-screen version of all the information
نسخة من المعلومات تملأ الشاشة
that we capture when we shoot virtual reality.
نلتقطها عند تصوير واقع افتراضي.
So we're shooting in every direction.
فنحن نصور من جميع الاتجاهات.
This is a camera system that we built
هذا هو نظام التصوير الذي قمنا ببنائه
that has 3D cameras that look in every direction
والذي يتضمن كاميرا ثلاثية الأبعاد تلتقط الصورة من كل الاتجاهات
and binaural microphones that face in every direction.
ومايكروفون لاقط للصوت من جميع الاتجاهات
We take this and we build, basically, a sphere of a world that you inhabit.
بهذه الأدوات نبني بشكل أساسي نموذجاً لعالم ستعيش فيه.
So what I'm going to show you is not a view into the world,
لذا فإن ما سأريك إياه ليس لقطة من داخل ذلك العالم.
it's basically the whole world stretched into a rectangle.
إنه فعلياً ذلك العالم بأكمله ضمن تلك الصورة
So this film is called "Clouds Over Sidra,"
اسم هذا الفيلم " غيوم فوق سيدرا"
and it was made in conjunction with our virtual reality company called VRSE
صنع بالتعاون مع شركتنا لإنتاج الواقع الافتراضي (VRSE)
and the United Nations,
ومع منظمة الأمم المتحدة
and a co-collaborator named Gabo Arora.
وبالتنسيق مع (جابو أرورا)
And we went to a Syrian refugee camp in Jordan in December
وذهبنا إلى مخيم للاجئين السوريين في الأردن في شهر ديسمبر
and shot the story of a 12-year-old girl there named Sidra.
وصورنا قصة طفلة تبلغ 12 سنة من العمر تدعى (سيدرا)
And she and her family fled Syria through the desert into Jordan
هربت مع عائلتها عبر الصحراء لتصل إلى الأردن
and she's been living in this camp for the last year and a half.
ولها الآن عام ونصف في ذلك المخيم
(Video) Sidra: My name is Sidra.
(فيديو) (سيدرا): أنا اسمي سيدرا
I am 12 years old.
عمري 12 سنة
I am in the fifth grade.
بالصف الخامس
I am from Syria, in the Daraa Province, Inkhil City.
أنا سوريّة، من محافظة درعا، مدينة انخل
I have lived here in the Zaatari camp in Jordan for the last year and a half.
أعيش هنا في مخيم الزعتري منذ عام ونصف
I have a big family:
عائلتي كبيرة:
three brothers, one is a baby.
لي ثلاثة أخوة، أحدهم رضيع.
He cries a lot.
إنه يبكي على الدوام.
I asked my father if I cried when I was a baby and he says I did not.
سألت والدي إذا كنت كثيرة البكاء عندما كنترضيعة، أجاب كلا
I think I was a stronger baby than my brother.
أظن أنني كنت أكثر قوة من أخي عندما كنت رضيعة
CM: So, when you're inside of the headset.
كريس ميلك: وهكذا، عندما تضع سماعاتك
you're not seeing it like this.
فإنك بهذا لن ترى صورة
You're looking around through this world.
بل ستتجول داخل ذلك العالم
You'll notice you see full 360 degrees, in all directions.
ستدرك أنك ضمن مساحة 360 درجة ترى المشهد من جميع الإتجاهات
And when you're sitting there in her room, watching her,
وعندما تراها جالسة هكذا في غرفتها،
you're not watching it through a television screen,
أنت لا تراها ضمن شاشة التلفاز
you're not watching it through a window, you're sitting there with her.
لا تراها من خلال نافذة، أنت تجلس معها حقيقة
When you look down, you're sitting on the same ground that she's sitting on.
إذا نظرت للأسفل، فستجد نفسك جالساً معها على نفس الأرضية
And because of that,
وبسبب هذا
you feel her humanity in a deeper way.
ستشعر بوجودها الإنساني بكل عمق
You empathize with her in a deeper way.
ستتعاطف معها بكل عمق
And I think that we can change minds with this machine.
أظن أننا بهذه الآلة نستطيع التأثير في العقول
And we've already started to try to change a few.
وبالفعل قد بدأنا المحاولة بتغيير البعض
So we took this film to the World Economic Forum in Davos in January.
فأخذنا هذا الفيلم إلى المنتدى الاقتصادي العالمي في دافوس في يناير
And we showed it to a group of people
وعرضناه على مجموعة من
whose decisions affect the lives of millions of people.
أصحاب القرار في قضايا تؤثر على ملايين الناس
And these are people who might not otherwise
هؤلاء الناس الذين قد لم يجلسوا يوماً
be sitting in a tent in a refugee camp in Jordan.
في خيمة ضمن مخيم اللاجئين في الأردن
But in January, one afternoon in Switzerland,
ولكنهم في يناير، في أحد الأيام و داخل سويسرا،
they suddenly all found themselves there.
وجدوا أنفسهم هناك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And they were affected by it.
وقد تأثروا بذلك.
So we're going to make more of them.
لذلك، سننتج المزيد من تلك الأفلام
We're working with the United Nations right now
نحن الآن وبالتعاون مع منظمة الأمم المتحدة
to shoot a whole series of these films.
بصدد تصوير سلسلة كاملة من تلك الأفلام
We just finished shooting a story in Liberia.
أنهينا للتو تصوير قصة في ليبيريا
And now, we're going to shoot a story in India.
وسنذهب لتصوير قصة في الهند
And we're taking these films,
وسنأخذ هذه الأفلام،
and we're showing them at the United Nations
وسنعرضها داخل منظمة الأمم المتحدة
to people that work there and people that are visiting there.
للعاملين والزائرين للمنظمة
And we're showing them to the people
سنعرضها للذين يملكون القدرة
that can actually change the lives of the people inside of the films.
على تغيير حياة الناس الموجودين في الفيلم.
And that's where I think we just start to scratch the surface
وبهذا نكون قد بدأنا باكتشاف
of the true power of virtual reality.
القوة الحقيقية للواقع الافتراضي.
It's not a video game peripheral.
هذه ليست لعبة فيديو لا جدوى منها
It connects humans to other humans in a profound way
إنها وسيلة تواصل عميقة للإنسانية
that I've never seen before in any other form of media.
لم اراها في أي وسيلة من وسائل الإعلام
And it can change people's perception of each other.
وسيلة قادرة على تغيير مفهاهيم البشر عن بعضهم البعض
And that's how I think
وهذا ما أراه
virtual reality has the potential to actually change the world.
من إمكانية للواقع الافتراضي لتغيير العالم.
So, it's a machine,
لذلك، هي آلة في النهاية
but through this machine we become more compassionate,
لكن من خلالها سنكون أكثر رحمة
we become more empathetic, and we become more connected.
أكثر تعاطفاً وتواصلاً
And ultimately, we become more human.
وفي النهاية، أكثر إنسانية
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)